字幕來源：射手網
■
后期：折翼的烏鴉兒
很久很久以前
A very long time ago...
在一塊名叫印度的神秘土地
...there lived a beautiful princess, in a mystical land known as...
住著一位美麗的公主
...India.
她嫁給了英俊的王子拉瑪
She was married to the handsome Prince Rama...
王子被惡毒的繼母凱伊皇后
...who had been banished to the enchanted forest...
流放到這座森林里來
...by his jealous stepmother, Queen Kaikeyi.
一天
One day...
西塔公主在森林里看見一只受傷的小鹿
...Princess Sita saw a wounded deer in the woods...
她肯求拉瑪王子去救它
...and she begged Rama to go and help it.
王子在地上畫了個圈  對公主說
Rama drew a circle in the ground and said to her:
這是一個魔法圈
"This is a magic circle.
只要你不離開它
So long as you stay inside it...
惡魔就不能傷害你
...no harm can come to you."
那天晚上  公主聽見一個聲音
That night, the princess heard a horrible cry.
救救我
Help me.
她以為是心愛的拉瑪王子有危險
Thinking it was her beloved Rama in danger...
于是跑出圈循著聲音跑去
...the princess ran from the circle to answer the cry.
不久遇見了一位年邁的乞丐
She soon came across an old beggar man.
盡管身無分文
Although she had no money to give him...
公主不忍心拒絕老人的哀求
...she could not refuse his plea.
就把自己的手鐲給了他
As soon as he had the bracelet...
就在這時乞丐變成了十頭怪獸  拉瓦納
...he transformed into the 10-headed demon, Ravana.
怪獸搶走了公主把她帶進魔宮
He grabs the princess and takes her to his palace...
強迫西塔作它的新娘
...where he attempts to make her his bride.
印度西姆拉  1914年
你見過真正的王子嗎  瑪亞
Did you ever know a real prince, Maya?
見過  拉其的父親
Yes, Laki's father.
-他不是個軍人嗎  -不錯
-I thought he was in the army.  -He was.
他是我的王子
And he was my prince.
我是他的公主
And I, his princess.
我說的是真正的王子和公主
But I mean real princes and princesses.
所有女人都是公主
All the women are princesses.
這是我們的權力
It is our right.
我會懷念這里
I shall miss it here.
印度是唯一能激起幻想的地方
India is the only place on earth that stirs the imagination.
真希望我們能永遠在這里
I wish we could stay here forever.
我知道  親愛的  但英格蘭正在打仗
I know, sweetheart. But now that England comes to war...
我必須參加戰役  這你能理解  對嗎
...I must go too. You understand that, don't you?
可我為什么非得去美國
But why must I go to America?
因為那里安全
Because it's safer.
你將要進
And besides, you'll be going to the same school
你母親上過的學校
your mother went to when she was your age...
-那城市叫  -紐約
- ...in a city called?  -New York.
爸爸
Papa?
瑪亞說所有的女孩都是公主
Maya told me that all girls are princesses.
瑪亞是個非常聰明的女人
Maya is a very wise woman.
那是真的了
Then it's true?
只要你相信  就能成為你希望的任何人
You can be anything you want to be, my lover, as long as you believe.
-那你相信什么  -我相信你是
-What do you believe?  -I believe that you are...
永遠是我的小公主
...and always will be, my little princess.
婚禮那天  我把這個送給了你母親
I gave this to your mother on our wedding day.
現在我把它送給你
I want you to have it.
她太美了
She was so beautiful.
你最愛她什么
What did you love most about her?
很難回答
Tough question.
她笑的時候  我愛她歡笑的眼睛
I loved the way her eyes lit up when she laughed.
你太像她了
Just like yours do.
她唱印度民謠時  我愛她美妙的歌聲
I loved the sound of her voice when she sang me the Indian folksong.
但我想  我最愛的
But I think, more than anything else...
是和她一起跳舞
...I loved dancing with her!
米切思女子學校  建于1856年
你好
Hello!
你一定是克魯上尉
You must be Captain Crewe.
我姐姐馬上就下來
My sister will be down presently.
我們正在為小姐準備房問
We were just preparing the young lady's room.
你漂亮的行李今早已經運到了
Your beautiful things arrived this morning.
謝謝  怎么稱呼
Thank you, er...?
天哪  愛米麗亞·米切思
Heavens, Amelia. Amelia Minchin.
克魯上尉
Captain Crewe.
見到你們真高興
How delightful to meet you!
這一定是小莎拉
And this must be little Sara.
多可愛的孩子
My, what a beautiful child.
我正在跟上尉說
I was telling the Captain...
謝謝  愛米麗亞  沒你的事了
Thank you, Amelia, that'll be all.
請跟我來
Now, won't you both follow me?
八點鐘開始上課
Classes begin promptly at 8:00.
這里教授所有課程  文學  數學  科學
We cover all subjects: literature, math, science...
當然還有法語和拉丁語
...and of course, both French and Latin.
莎拉會說流利的
Oh, Sara speaks fluent...
午餐一點半  然后是例行的散步
Luncheon is served at 1:30. After we take our daily walk...
除非天氣異常惡劣
...unless the weather is extremely inclement.
四點是禮儀課
At 4:00, the girls attend etiquette classes...
孩子們可以學到高雅的舉止
...where they're trained in the formal graces of society.
四點半到六點半在大教室學習  之后是晚餐
Study hall is between 4:30 and 6:30, followed by a light supper.
就寢前  我們閱讀名著
Before then bedtime, we read from one of the classics...
這是孩子們最樂意參加的
...something the children look forward to be great attanding anticipation.
星期天休息
Sunday is a day of rest.
學生們可以寫信  不過只能寫給自己的父母
Students may write only to their parents.
當然  我們也要去教堂  您還有什么問題嗎
And of course, we attend church. Have you any questions?
過來  親愛的
Come along, dear.
我吃  你吃
Je mange, tu manges
打擾一下  杜弗吉先生
Excusez-moi, monsieur Dufarge
姑娘們
Girls.
向新同學莎拉·克魯小姐問好
I would like you to say hello to our new arrival...Miss Sara Crewe.
你好  莎拉
Hello, Sara.
把你在印度的生活告訴她們
You must tell them all about your exciting life in India.
她很快會成為最受歡迎的學生
No doubt she'll be our most popular student in no time.
還有些規則要對你說清楚
Now, there are certain rules that should be made quite clear.
首先是秩序
The first is the Order Rule...
孩子們必須保持房間整潔
...which requires the girls keep their rooms spotless.
這些規則必須嚴格遵守
These rules are strictly enforced.
我向你保證  克魯上尉  這是卓有成效的
But I assure you, Captain Crewe, the results are well worth the effort.
我們的宗旨是培養出最優雅
Our reputation for sending the most poised...
高貴的小姐進入社交界
...and charming young ladies into society is one of the highest.
毫無疑問
I've no doubt.
在這里不許佩戴珠寶手飾
Also, I'm afraid jewelry and such finery are not allowed.
休息時在自己的房間里呢
What if I wear it in my room, during my free time?
如果你一定堅持的話
Well, if you absolutely insist.
我堅持
I do.
她會惹麻煩
She's gona get so much trouble.
先生
Monsieur.
-我吃  -我吃
-je mange  -je mange
-你吃  -你吃
-tu manges  -tu manges
這里真不錯
This is splendid.
這是我們最大的套房
It's our largest suite.
感謝你所做的一切  米切思小姐
Thank you for all the care you've taken, Miss Minchin.
希望我走后莎拉在這里能像在家一樣
I want Sara to feel as much as possible at home while I'm away.
-請不必在乎費用  -當然
-No expense shall be spared.  -Of course not.
我該讓你們互相道別了
Now I'll let you two say goodbye.
您出發的時間快到了
I konw you don't have much time before your boat leaves.
我們每天寫一封信
We'll write to each other every day.
喜歡你的房間嗎
How do you like your room?
我想它是最好的  有朝街的窗戶和壁爐
I made sure it was the best, with corner windows and a fireplace.
你的玩具和衣服都在這里
And with all your toys and clothes moved in...
就像在家里
...it's as if you were really...
我看見了一樣東西
I think I saw something...
就在那里
...on that chair over there.
她是專程從法國來陪伴你的
She came all the way from France juse to be with you.
她叫愛米麗
Her name is Emily.
愛米麗
Emily.
洋娃娃是女孩子最好的朋友
You know dolls make the very best friends.
她不會說話并不表示聽不懂
Just because they can't speak doesn't mean they don't listen.
知道嗎  我們離開房問  她就變活了
And did you know, when we leave them alone in our room, they come to life?
-真的  -當然
-They do?  -Yes.
我們進來前她又會變成洋娃娃  快得像閃電
Before we walk in, they quickly return to their places. Quick likes light!
她為什么不在我們面前活過來
Why don't they come to life in front of us so that we can see them?
因為這是魔法
Because it's magic.
你要相信它
Magic has to be believed.
這樣才能顯靈
That's the only way it's real.
你害怕時  想我時
Whenever you're afraid, or miss me terribly...
就告訴愛米麗
...just tell Emily.
不管我在哪里她都會告訴我
She'll get the message to me, wherever I am.
我會馬上給你回信
And I'll send one back right away...
你摟著愛米麗
...so when you hug her...
就像摟著我一樣
...you'll be getting a hug from me.
我答應你  爸爸
It's all right, Papa.
我會好好的
I'm going to be fine.
你在做什么
What are you doing?
用心記住我
Memorizing me by heart?
你早已在我心里了
No, I already know you by heart.
再見  小公主
Goodbye princess.
昨晚怎么那么吵
What was that noise last night?
有人哭了幾個小時
Somebody was crying for hours.
那算什么  你應該聽聽喬瑟芬打呼嚕
That's nothing. You should hear Josephine snore.
我不打呼嚕
I do not!
她是誰  -那個新來的女孩
-Who was it?  -The new girl?
她還沒出過她的房問  你見過她的玩具嗎
She hasn't come out of her room yet. Did you see all her toys?
給我你的絲帶
I want your hair ribbon.
她父親制造餅干之類的  他們很有錢
Her father grows crackers or something. They're very rich.
那當然  我認識的每個人都喜歡吃餅干
They must be. Everyone I know eats crackers.
她父親是英國人  聽說跟國王和王后是好朋友
Her father's British. I hear he's best friends with the king and queen.
聽說他被流放到印度
Well, I hear he was thrown out of India...
因為他做有毒的餅干害死許多人
...because people died from eating his poisoned crackers.
有毒的餅干
Poisoned crackers?
我姨媽是吃了有毒的豆子死了
My aunt once died from eating poisoned string beans.
-誰在乎你姨媽  -就是  誰在乎
-Who cares about her?  -Yeah, who cares?
我們進來前她又會變成娃娃
But before we walk in and catch them, they return to their places,
快得像閃電
quick as lightning.
天哪  真夠快的
Gosh, she's fast.
媽媽
Mama.
莎拉
Sara?
不能因為一個人耽誤大家的早餐
We are not customed to delay everyone's breakfast for one student.
對不起  可我
I'm sorry, Miss Minchin, but I found my mama...
記住  你不是這里唯一的孩子
You're not the only child here, Sara, you have to remember that.
早安
Yes, yes, yes, good morning.
記得昨天來的那位小姐嗎
I trust you remember our newest pupil from our visit to class yesterday.
莎拉  這位是杜弗吉先生
Sara, this is Monsieur Dufarge.
今天下午你向他學習法語
You willl begin French lessons with him this afternoon.
我非得學嗎
Do I have to?
你當然非學不可
Sara, you most certainly do.
為你的失禮向杜弗吉先生道歉
Now apologize to Monsieur this instance for your rudeness.
-對不起  我不是想冒犯他  -道歉
-But I didn't mean to be rude.  -Now!
這孩子不需要再學法語了  她說得很好
This child doesn't need to learn French. She practically is French!
她的法語很好  跟他爸爸學的
She learned from her father.
我非常清楚她說什么
I understood perfectly well what she said, Monsieur.
我們想告訴您的
I'm sorry.  But we tried to tell you.
她可以去教小一點的孩子
Well, perhaps She can tutor the younger children...
或許她還能幫您糾正發音
...and just be able to help you with your pronunciation, Miss Minchin.
我聞到的是香腸味嗎
Are those sausages I smell?
謝謝
Thank you.
餐桌上不許講話
Sara, there's no talking at the table.
這不正常
Doesn't seem natural.
我不想再重復
I won't say it again.
7乘以5是35
Seven times five is 35.
7乘以6是42
Seven times six is 42.
7乘以7是49
Seven times seven is 49.
7乘以8是
Seven times eight is...
...58.
不  等等  54
No, wait. 54?
72  93  還是12
Or 72? Or 93? Or 12?
對不起  米切思小姐
I'm sorry, Miss Minchin.
昨晚我背了幾個小時
I studied for hours last night.
我簡直不敢相信
I find that very hard to believe.
我想你父親應該知道這些
And I imagine your father will as well.
求你別告訴他
Please don't tell him, Miss Minchin.
我保證下次會做對
I promise I'll do better.
求你了
Please.
拉維妮亞  你來算
Lavinia, you may continue.
7乘以8是56
Seven times eight is 56.
7乘以9
Seven times nine...
是63
...is 63.
親愛的爸爸
Dear Papa:
我已經開始想你了
I miss you already.
這里一切都好
Things are fine.
只是我沒想到學校有這么多規矩
Except I never imagined there would be so many rules at school.
我想它們存在一定有道理
I guess they're there for a purpose...
我正努力去遵守
...and I'm trying hard to obey them.
但我還是覺得我做錯了什么
But I get the feeling I'm doing something wrong.
再見  爸爸
Goodbye, Father.
再見  我的孩子
Bye, son.
希望你讀這封信的時候
I hope when you read this...
臉上帶著微笑  心里充滿快樂
...it kindles your heart and puts a smile on your face.
我真的為你驕傲  每時每刻都在思念著你
Papa, I'm so proud of you. And I think about you every moment.
永遠永遠愛你
And I love you forever.
你的莎拉
Your Sara.
洛蒂  再別鬧了
Lottie, you mustn't get so excited.
洛蒂  親愛的
Lottie? Precious?
求你了  洛蒂寶貝  別再叫了
Oh, please, Lottie dear! Please stop screaming!
想不想吃餅干  要吃嗎
How about a cookie? Would you like that?
我去給你拿
I'll get a cookie.
你這樣鬧別人都沒法學習了
It's very hard to study with you carrying on like this.
我要媽媽
I want my mama!
你很快就會見到她
You'll see her soon.
不會  她死了  我再見不到她了
No, I won't. She's dead, and I won't ever see her again!
我也沒有媽媽
Well, I don't have a mother either.
是嗎
You don't?
她在哪
Where is she?
在天堂  和我小妹妹在一起
In heaven with my baby sister.
這不意味著我不能和她說話
That doesn't mean I can't talk to her.
我什么都跟她說  我知道她聽得見
I tell her everything, I know she hears me.
怎么會
How?
因為天使都能聽見
Because that's what angels do.
-你媽媽是天使  -當然
-Your mama's an angel?  -Of course.
你的媽媽也是 有美麗的絲翅膀
And so is yours. With beautiful wings of silk...
戴著玫瑰花冠
...and a crown of baby rosebuds.
她們都住在城堡里
And they all live together in a castle.
知道城堡是什么造的嗎
Do you know what it's made of?
是向日葵
Sunflowers...
幾千朵向日葵像黃金一般閃著光芒
...hundreds of them, so bright they shine like gold.
天使們想去什么地方
When the angels want to go someplace...
就吹口哨  像這樣
...they just whistle, like this.
云彩飛到城堡大門帶上她們
And a cloud floats to the castle and picks them up.
天使飛向天空
As the angels fly through the sky...
就像坐著魔毯
...riding the cloud like a magic carpet...
在月光下穿梭于星星之問
...under the moon and through the stars...
直至飛到我們頭頂上
...until they're hovering right above us.
她們在天上注視著我們是否快樂
That's how they can look down and see if we're all right.
有時她們會給我們捎話
And sometimes they even send messages to us.
你這樣又哭又鬧
Of course, you can't hear the messages
就聽不見她們說什么了
if you're kicking and screaming as loudly as you were.
不過她們會再說好幾遍  怕我們沒聽見
But they always try again, just in case we've missed it.
等等
Hey, wait!
那是貝琪  她不能跟我們講話
That's Becky. She's not allowed to talk to us.
為什么
Why not?
她是女傭而且是個黑人
She's a servant girl, and she has dark skin.
那又怎么樣
So?
這還不夠嗎
Well, doesn't that mean something?
對不起  我不是
I'm sorry, I...
需要我為你做什么  小姐
Is there anything I can do for you, miss?
我只是上樓來換鞋
I just came up here to change my shoes.
不  沒什么
No, there's nothing.
請原諒  可你待在這里我們都會有麻煩
Well, then begging your pardon, but we'll both be in trouble if you stay.
好了  姑娘們  排好隊
All right, girls, pair up.
排好隊
Pair up.
親愛的貝琪  希望我們能成為朋友  莎拉
愛德華爵士看見女兒眼里的憂傷
"Sir Edward saw the sorrow in his daughter's eyes...
但他知道家族榮譽是首要的
...but he knew that family honor must prevail at all costs.
貴族身份不能被忽視
Nobility was not thought to be trifled with.
"我向你求婚  夏洛特"  他說
'I beg of you, Charlotte,' he said.
"答應約翰爵士春天嫁給他"
'Marry Sir John in the spring, as he has asked.'
謝謝  拉維妮亞
Thank you, Lavinia.
莎拉  你接著讀
Sara, you may take your turn.
夏洛特轉過身對父親說  "父親  你是對的"
"Charlotte turned to her father and said, 'Father, you are right.
"我必須打消那愚蠢瘋狂幼稚的想法"
'I must put away my foolish fancies and childhood wishes.'
但我不想那么做
But I simply won't do it.
對不起  父親
I'm sorry, Father.
我不能嫁給我不愛的人
When I marry, it'll be for love.
說著  夏洛特沖出房子
And with that, Charlotte ran from the house.
在外面等待她的是英俊的馬夫  皮埃爾
Waiting outside was the handsome stable boy, Pierre...
夏洛特心愛的王子
...whom Charlotte secretly adored.
他們逃到海邊
Together they escaped to the coast
坐船去塔帝島
and quickly set sail to the island for Tahiti.
途中遭到
But when they were halfway there,
一幫海盜的襲擊
their ship was attacked by band of pirates!
不想被活著吃掉
Rather than be eaten alive...
夏洛特和皮埃爾跳進洶涌的大海
...Charlotte and Pierre threw themselves into the raging sea.
在他們將要被淹沒時
As they began to drown...
緊緊擁抱著山盟海誓
...they held each other close, and swore undying love.
絕望之際一群美人魚出現
But then, when all seemed lost, a group of mermaids appeared and rescued...
別說了
Stop!
你在干什么
What are you doing?
我不忍心看她嫁給那個人
I couldn't bear to see Charlotte marry that man,
就想像了另一個結局
so I imagined a different ending.
你想像的
Imagined it?
您從來不這樣嗎
Don't you ever do that, Miss Minchin?
相信某種東西  讓它像是真的
Believe in something, just to make it seem real?
什么都不缺的孩子才會想像
That's easy for a child who has everything.
學校里不允許想像
There will be no more make-believe at this school...
閱讀時間或其他時間都不允許
...during reading or any other time.
-明白了嗎  -是  米切思小姐
-Is that understood?  -Yes, Miss Minchin.
都回房間去
All of you, go to your bed this instant.
我從沒聽過這么好聽的故事
I never heard a story like that in my whole life.
你一定知道很多故事  對嗎  莎拉
I...I bet you know lots of them, don't you, Sara?
不許說話
I want silence up there!
我們得想法怎么對付這些規矩
We have to do something about this communication rule.
等米切思小姐睡著后
Hey, after Minchin goes to bed...
我們去你房間聽你給我們講故事
...we'll sneak into your room, and you can tell us a real story is.
行嗎  莎拉
How about it, Sara?
只能你們三個人來
Only if it's just you three.
快來  快來
Come on, come on.
怪獸拉瓦納把公主鎖在魔宮的塔樓上
The evil Ravana locked the princess up in his palace tower.
好幾個星期
There she stayed for many weeks...
公主看著窗外
...just staring out her window...
非常思念她的王子
...missing her Prince Rama terribly.
你真漂亮  就像愛米麗
Perfect. You look just like Emily.
我父親討厭洋娃娃  他不愿意來看我
My father hates dolls. And he hates coming here.
說他不屬于這里
Says he doesn't belong.
那他為什么送你來
Then why does he send you?
他想給我找個地方住
Because he wants me to belong.
我的小女兒  她會說法語  她真的會說法語
My little girl. She spoke French! She really spoke French.
我和你母親為你自豪
Your mother and I are very proud of you.
我抓到你了
I caught you, Nellie!
爸爸
Papa!
蘭道夫  喬思
Randolph... John!
拉瑪王子向魔宮走去
Rama approached the thorny palace...
他不知道怪獸拉瓦納正在等著他
...unaware that Ravana was waiting for him.
好了  我受夠了
That's it! I can't take it anymore!
我才不管你說什么
I don't care what you say about Sara's stories.
她的故事比看你梳頭有趣得多
They' ve got to be more fun than watching your hair being combed!
如果還有人這么想  可以馬上走
If anyone else feels the same way, I think she should leave too.
怪獸拉瓦納還沒出來
But the evil Ravana was not through yet.
這次它舉起一張弓和十枝箭
This one, he took a bow that could hold, not one, but 10 arrows...
每枝箭頭上都抹了毒藥
...each filled with the deadly poison.
箭劃破長空
The arrows sped through the air...
對準王子飛過來
...heading straight for Rama.
箭射到地上
And the arrows hit the ground...
放出毒氣  冒出一股黃色的濃煙
...and released their poison, giant clouds of thick, yellow smoke.
-我想要一塊大的蛋糕  -快點  洛蒂
-I want a big piece!  -Oh, hush up, Lottie.
莎拉公主會很公平
I am sure "Princess" Sara will give everyone a fair share.
對嗎  公主
Right, Princess?
我告訴她你是公主
I told her that's what you were.
不只是我  所有女孩都是公主
Well, not just me. All girls are princesses.
包括像你一樣壞脾氣的女孩
Even snotty, two-faced bullies like you, Lavinia.
拉維妮亞  給你一塊大的
Here, Lavinia, you get a big piece.
米切思小姐
Miss Minchin?
是的  有什么事嗎
Yes, may I help you?
我叫巴洛
I'm Mr. Barrow.
是克魯上尉的律師
Captain Crewe's solicitor.
請進來吧
Oh, yes, do come in.
我們正在為莎拉慶祝生日
We're just celebrating little Sara's birthday.
能和您私下談談嗎
May I speak to you in private?
當然可以  請跟我來
Oh, yes, of course. Right this way.
您看見了  莎拉在這里很受歡迎
May I just say is about that Sara is quite the favorite around here.
我們為她的生日做了精心準備
We went to great lengths to make this a special day for her.
恐怕這個月的支票數額會很大
I'm afraid your check to us this month will be rather large.
不會再有支票了  米切思小姐
There will be no check, Miss Minchin.
您說什么
Excuse me?
生日聚會結束  你們立即回自己房間去
The party is over! I want everyone go to their rooms, this instant!
可是我們
But Miss Minchin, we...
莎拉  你留下
Sara, you will stay behind.
有件事要告訴你
I have something to tell you.
快走
Move!
愛米麗亞  到莎拉房間找件黑衣服
Amelia, go to Sara's room and find a simple black dress.
要是沒有合適的  先借一件
If nothing is suitable, borrow one from other girls.
-可是  姐姐  -按我說的去做
-But, sister, I...  -Do as I say.
我為什么需要黑衣服
Why would I need a black dress, Miss Minchin?
因為有個壞消息  莎拉
I'm afraid I have some bad news, Sara.
你父親
Your father has...
Your father...
你父親已經死了
It's been discovered that your father has died.
幾個星期前他陣亡了
He was killed in battle several weeks ago.
我很遺憾
I'm sorry.
但這是事實
That's the reality, the situation,
無人能改變
and there's nothing anyone can do to change it.
還有  英國政府沒收了他的公司
What's more, the British government has seized control of his company
和所有財產
and all of his assets...
沒給你留下一分錢
...leaving you penniless, without any money.
你沒有別的親戚  這讓我很為難
And since you've no relations, this puts me in a terrible position.
你看什么
What are you staring at?
不明白我的話嗎
Don't you understand what I'm saying?
你現在在這世上無依無靠
You are alone in the world...
只有我可憐你決定讓你留在這里
...unless I decide to keep you here out of charity.
你欠了債
Because of the expenses you've incurred,
你所有東西都歸我了
everything you own now belongs to me...
你的衣服  玩具  所有東西
...your clothes, your toys, everything.
但這還不足以彌補我的損失
But they'll hardly make up for the financial losses I've suffered.
從現在起你必須自己養活自己
From now on, you must earn your room and board here.
搬到閣樓上和貝琪一塊住  現在你是傭人
You'll move to the attic with Becky and work as a servant.
你要是不好好地干活
If you fail to meet the standards in this institution...
或是不老實  我就把你趕出去
...or if you don't do as told, you'll be thrown out.
相信我
Believe me, Sara,
這個城市的街道不會可憐你這種小乞丐
the streets of this city are not kind to homeless beggars.
早上5點到廚房去干活
Report to Mabel in the kitchen promptly at 5 a.m.
帶著這個你會被抓起來
I could you'll be arrested for taking this.
你很走運我把那洋娃娃留給你
You're lucky I let you keep that doll.
書也給你
You may have the book.
再出這種事我就叫警察
But another incident like this and I will call the authorities.
你要記住  莎拉·克魯
I expect you to remember, Sara Crewe...
你不再是公主了
...you're not a princess any longer.
爸爸
Papa.
爸爸  回來吧
Papa, please.
爸爸
Papa.
莎拉  怎么了
Sara, what happened?
伺候小姐不必說話  明白嗎
You're to serve the girls without conversation, you understand?
今后莎拉是這里的傭人
Sara will be working here as a servant from now on.
你們不許和她說話  知道了嗎
There will be no communication exchange. Is that clear?
是  米切思小姐
Yes, Miss Minchin.
7乘以5是35
Seven times five is 35.
7乘以6是42
Seven times six is 42.
放開我
Let go!
我的天
Great God!
這不是真的
It can't be!
是我兒子  喬思
It's my son, John!
天哪  不
Dear God, no.
不是喬思
Not John.
是喬思  拉姆·戴斯
It's John, Ram Dass!
是喬思  幫幫我
It's John. Help me.
-進去吧  -幫我
-Come inside.  -Help.
我以為你睡著了
On, I thought you'd be sleeping.
我還沒機會送你生日禮物
I never got a chance to give you your birthday present.
這是你住過的地方
It's a picture of where you used to live.
看這藍色的線  這是河
See the blue threads? That's the river.
這些是你常常提起的山
These are the mountains you always talk about.
貝琪  謝謝你
Thank you, Becky.
它太美了
It's beautiful.
莎拉
Sara
你怎么不再講故事了
Why don't you tell stories anymore?
那都是想像  沒有任何意義
They're just make-believe. They don't mean anything.
但對我很有意義
On, but they've always meant something to me.
有時我覺得如果聽不到你那些神奇的故事我會死
Some days I thought I'd die, until I heard you talk about the magic.
世界上沒有什么神奇的故事
There is no magic, Becky.
爸爸
Papa...
你聽到了嗎
...can you hear me?
我好害伯
I'm so scared.
你還是公主嗎
Are you still a princess?
你快回去吧  不然我們都有惹麻煩
You better get back in line or we'll both be in trouble.
你還是嗎
Are you?
洛蒂
Lottie!
姑娘們  排好隊
All right, girls, get in line.
別碰那個
Don't touch that!
那是給隔壁蘭道夫先生的
It's for Mr. Randolph, next door.
可憐的老人  他兒子在歐洲犧牲了
The poor man. His son is missing in action in Europe.
你說喬思  他是個好孩子
You mean John? He's such a nice boy.
給  小姑娘
Here, little girl.
我跟你說過別給乞丐錢
I told you not to give your money away.
對不起  等一等
Excuse me. Excuse me.
看見了吧  他們最會纏人
You see? You never get rid of them.
你要買什么
May I help you?
要花嗎  請買朵花吧
Would you like to buy a flower?
買花吧
-你要花嗎  -今天不要
-Would you?  -Not today.
你要買花嗎
Sir, would you like to buy a flower?
請買朵花吧
Would you?
先生  請買朵花吧
Would you like a flower, sir?
讓一讓
Pardon me.
您要花嗎
Would you like a flower?
送她一朵花
Give her a flower.
等等
Wait!
送給小公主
For the princess.
你怎么了  小老鼠
What is it, little mouse?
你也是個囚犯嗎
Are you a prisoner too?
你來的那個地方也這么冷嗎
Is it ever this cold where you come from?
不
No.
跟我說說  莎拉  再給我講講印度
Tell me about it, Sara. Tell me again about India.
印度
India.
講吧
Tell me.
好吧
Well...
那里的空氣非常熱
...the air is so hot there...
你似乎能嘗到那味道
...you can almost taste it.
那滋味一定像椰子
I bet it tastes like coconuts.
不  更像香料
No, it's more like spices, really.
咖哩和番紅花
Curry and saffron.
還有什么
What else?
老虎在樹下睡覺
Tigers sleep under trees...
大象在湖里洗澡納涼
...and elephants cool themselves in the lakes.
暖風吹過原野
The warm wind blows through the fields...
精靈們乘著風
...and the spirits ride it...
唱著歌在天上注視著我們
...singing as they look down on us.
她們的聲音在山谷問回蕩
Their voices echo through the mountains...
天空
...and the sky...
呈現出繽紛色彩
...is all different colors...
像孔雀羽毛
...like a peacock's tail.
把煤煙灰弄得到處都是  愚貨
Soot all over the place, you clumsy fool!
滾
Get out!
馬上滾出去
Get out of my house!
這星期別指望能拿到一分錢
And you can forget being paid this week!
忘思負義的小東西
Ungrateful little wretch.
別向我要錢
No, you don't!
我說過屋里不許有一點煤灰
I told I won't tolerate any soot in this house!
看看我的靴子  全被搞臟了
And there, just look at my boot! It's filthy!
快滾
Out!
拿上你的破玩意滾吧
Out! And take this ridiculous-looking thing with you!
愛米麗亞小姐在哪
Where, where might Miss Amelia be this morning?
早安  法蘭西斯  你今天來得真早
Good morning, Frances. You're here early this morning.
男人想有成就必須勤快一些
A working man gets up early if he wants to have an effect on the world.
說得對
How true.
你的精神令人欽佩  法蘭西斯
And what a powerful effect you have, Frances.
你去哪了
Where have you been?
我已經被凍了半個鐘頭了  快把火點上
I've been chilled for half an hour. Hurry up and light a fire.
別用你的臟手碰任何東西
And don't touch anything else with your dirty hands.
現在這房間是我的了  不準你把它弄臟了
This is my room now, and I won't have you messing it up.
這是什么味道真惡心
What is that awful smell?
你上次洗澡是什么時候
When was your last time you had a bath?
你在干什么
What are you doing?
我不相信這一套
I don't believe in this!
你快停下  停下
So you can just stop it! Stop it, I said!
那是什么意思
What did you just do?
幾句跟印度女巫學的咒話
Just a little curse I learned from a witch in India.
咒語
Curse?
-什么樣的咒語  -你會知道的
-What kind of curse?  -You'll see.
不過我要是你就不那樣梳頭
But I wouldn't brush my hair as much if I were you.
過來吧  這是我專門為你留的
It's all right. I saved it especially for you.
來吧  吃吧
Go on. Take it.
你就住在這里
Is this where you live?
你不該來  這太冒險了
You shouldn't be here. It's too dangerous.
為什么你不再喜歡我了  我做錯了什么嗎
Sara, why don't you like me anymore? Did I do something wrong?
沒有  當然沒有
No, of course not.
我以為你們不想再和我交朋友
I didn't think you'd want me for a friend...
畢竟一切都變了
...now that things are different.
我知道你沒有我這個朋友也很好
Sara, no, I'm sure you could do just fine without me for a friend...
可我不能沒有你
...but I couldn't get along without you.
對不起  我應該想到
I'm sorry. I should've known...
你和別人不同
...you wouldn't be like the others.
-什么聲音  -敲一聲表示"我在這里"
-What's that?  -One knock means "I'm here."
敲兩聲表示"一切都好"
Two knocks means "All is well."
敲三聲就是"沒有危險"
Three means "The coast is clear."
"米切思女巫已經睡了"
'The demon Minchinweed is asleep.'
這太刺激了
Gosh! It all sounds so adventurous!
貝琪  來客人了
Look, Becky. We have a visitor.
你好  貝琪
Hello, Becky.
莎拉  我太想聽你講故事了
Oh, Sara, I miss your stories so much.
告訴我們公主和王子后來怎樣了
Won't you tell us what happened to Rama and the princess?
黃色的毒煙
The smoke from Ravana's arrows...
終于散開
...finally began to lift.
拉瑪倒在地上一動也不動
Rama lay dead on the ground.
不
Oh, no!
但是神奇的事發生了
But then a wonderful thing happened.
一只羚羊來到王子身邊  用自己的生命救活了他
The gazelle laid down next to Rama, giving him his own life.
他患有暫時性失憶癥
He's suffering from cute amnesia...
是毒氣彈的副作用
...one of the rare side effects of poison gas.
他的視力很快就會恢復
His eyes will heal in time.
他的記憶就很難說了
His memory... who can say?
他不是我兒子
He's not my son.
很抱歉  蘭道夫先生
I'm sorry, Mr. Randolph.
他被發現時身受重傷
He was found in severe shock...
沒有軍服  沒有證件
...with no coat, no identification.
因為只有您兒子還沒找到
Since your son was the only name unaccounted for...
所以他們認為這是喬思
...they assumed this was John.
很對不起
I am sorry.
沒希望了  你認為我是個傻瓜
All the hoping. You must think me a fool.
您希望自己是個聰明人  主人
Is it your wish to be wise, sahib?
我不知道
I don't know.
一個聰明人根本不會來這里
I suppose a wise man wouldn't have come here at all.
聰明人
But if he had...
會再仔細看看這位軍官
...he would have looked closely upon the soldier's face.
能看出什么
What would he have seen?
痛苦  先生  他需要照顧
Pain, sahib. He needs to be cared for.
這不是我的責任
He's not my responsibility.
聰明人記得他和喬思在一個軍團
A wise man would remember that this soldior was in John's regiment.
如果他恢復記憶或許能告訴先生
If his memory returns, he might tell us what happened to his son.
喬思正在英國某醫院里
Perhaps sahib will learn that John is in British hospital...
等待著好心人幫他脫離痛苦  帶他回家
...wishing that a kind man would take him home, away from his pain.
管道工來了  告訴他哪壞了
If the plumber comes, show him the problem.
別和他聊天  他可是計時收費
And don't babble with this man. He's paid by the hour.
我回來之前把拉丁文試卷判好
And make sure to correct the Latin tests by the time I get back.
是  姐姐
Yes, sister.
您好  米切思小姐
Hello, Miss Minchin.
再見  米切思小姐
Goodbye, Miss Minchin.
不  別這樣
Oh, no, not again!
洛蒂  別這樣
Lottie, not again.
快找那條項鍵
Let's find the locket.
好了
All right...
別鬧了
...it's okay. It's all right.
我想洛蒂中邪了
Sara, come quick! It's Lottie, I think Lottie's possessed.
找到了
I got it.
你去管住那個小東西好嗎
Will you please get that child under control?
別擔心  一切都好
Don't worry. Everything's fine.
你怎么了
Well, what is it?
我想我看見了老鼠
I thought I saw a mouse.
你好
Hello.
那孩子是撤旦派來折磨我的
I swear, that child has a pact with Satan to destroy me.
這工作不適合我  我沒有耐心
I'm not cut out for this job. I have no patience for children.
教書要記住那么多可怕的東西
And teaching! All those horrible facts to remember.
我簡直煩透了
I don't like it at all.
你喜歡法蘭西斯  是嗎
You like Frances, don't you?
什么
What?
當然不是  你怎么敢這么說
Of course not. How dare you.
我想他也喜歡你
I think he likes you too.
是嗎
You do?
真的
Really?
你們應該遠走高飛去結婚
I think you should run away and get married.
這該有多浪漫
It'd be terribly romantic.
多么令人激動
What an extraordinary thing to say.
可是我姐姐知道了會大發雷雷
Well, anyway, my sister would be furious if she found out.
那時你早走遠了
So, you'd be long gone by then.
和勇敢的法蘭西斯一起
Living in some exotic paradise...
生活在你們的伊甸園里
...with that dashing young milkman.
我得去集市了
I'd better get to the market.
你做得很好  年輕人
You're doing well, young man.
你馬上就到家了
You're almost home.
請相信我的眼睛  主人
You must trust my eyes, sahib.
怎么回事
What's going on?
一個驚喜
It's a surprise.
-你們怎么來了  -我們給你帶來樣東西
-What are you doing here?  - We brought you something.
莎拉公主  我們為你找回了一件東西
Princess Sara, we like to present you with something we rescued.
歷經驚心動魄的歷險
In a dangerous adventure.
-我們自己的軍事行動  -冒著生命危險
-Our very own crusade.  -Risking all our lives.
還有我
And mine too.
我不知道該說什么
I don't know what to say.
你們是我最好的朋友
You are the best friends anyone could ever ask for.
沒事的  這是我的小朋友  漢納曼
It's all right. It's just my little monkey friend, Hanuman.
他是從哪來的
Where did he come from?
就是隔壁  看
Right next door. Look.
漢納曼喜歡來做客
Hanuman likes to come to visit me all the time.
你能和他說話嗎
Can you really talk to him, Sara?
當然
Sure!
漢納曼  跟我的朋友們打個招呼
Hanuman, say hello to all my friends.
拉瑪醒來后
After Rama came back to life...
跑到怪獸的魔宮去救公主
...he raced towards the monster's palace to rescue Sita.
可是突然
Suddenly...
拉瓦納出現了
...Ravana appeared!
我們還是以后再接著講吧
I think we better save the rest of the story for later.
你們在這里干什么
What's going on here?
不是她們的錯  是我叫她們來的
It's not their fault. I asked them to come.
你們五個立即下樓
You five go downstairs immediately.
以后再處理
I'll deal with you later.
貝琪
Becky...
你明天關在自己的屋里
...you'll remain locked in your room for the entire day tomorrow
別想吃飯
without meals.
快走
Go!
她的活也歸你干
And you will perform all her chores in addition to your own...
并且沒有早餐  午餐和晚餐
...without breakfast, lunch or dinner.
你應該明白
It's time you learned, Sara Crewe...
現實生活不是你幻想的故事
...that real life has nothing to do with your fantasy games.
這是個殘酷骯臟的世界
It's a cruel, nasty world out there...
我們的責任就是盡量做到最好
...and it's our duty to make the best of it.
不要沉浸在愚蠢的幻想中  而是讓自己成為有用的人
Not to indulge in ridiculous dreams, but to be productive and useful.
聽明白我的話了嗎
Do you understand what I'm saying?
是的  女士
Yes, ma'am.
很好
Good.
可我并不相信
But I don't believe in it.
別跟我說你仍舊是什么公主
Don't tell me you still fancy yourself a princess.
上帝  看看你周圍
Good God, child, look around you!
去照照鏡子
Or better yet, look in the mirror.
我是公主
I am a princess.
所有的女孩都是
All girls are.
即使她們住在窄小的閣樓上
Even if they live in tiny old attics.
即使她們穿得破破爛爛
Even if they dress in rags.
即使她們不漂亮不聰明不再年輕
Even if they aren't pretty or smart or young.
她們還是公主  我們全都是
They're still princesses. All of us.
您父親沒有告訴過你
Didn't your father ever tell you that?
他沒有嗎
Didn't he?
我再發現你和別的女孩在這里
If I find you up here with any other girls again...
就把你扔到街上去
...I'll throw you out into the street!
我們該怎么辦
What're we going to do?
整天都會沒有飯吃
A whole day with nothing to eat.
貝琪  別哭
Don't cry, Becky.
我很害伯
I'm scared.
如果米切思把我趕走  我沒有地方可去
If Minchin throws me out, I've got no place to go.
放心吧
That's not true.
我會陪著你  我一直覺得我們是姐妹
I'm here with you. I've always thought of us as sisters.
是真的
You have?
我們發誓永遠照顧對方
Let's make a promise riight now to always look out for each other.
我發誓
It's a promise.
現在怎么能找點吃的呢
Now, what are we going to do about food?
我們會餓死的
Starve, I guess.
不會  我們要做一件事
No, there's only one thing to do.
睡覺前吃一頓豐盛的晚宴
We'll eat a great feast before we go to sleep...
這樣明天就不會覺得餓
...and that will keep us full all day tomorrow.
晚宴  什么晚宴
Feast? What feast?
你看
Just look around.
看見那邊的桌子了嗎
Do you see that table there?
鋪著潔白的臺布
It's covered with a beautiful cloth...
還有蠟燭
...and candles...
托盤里放著各種美味可口的食物
...and trays of good things to eat.
來吧  貝琪
Come on, Becky.
告訴我那上面都有什么
Tell me what kind of food there is.
可我什么也沒看見
But I don't see any food.
試試看  貝琪
Try, Becky.
想像那里有  記得你對我說的話嗎
Just make-believe it. Remember what you told me?
神奇的魔法
About the magic?
-小松餅  -很好  什么樣的
-Muffins?  -Good! What kind?
各種各樣的
All kinds.
都是最好的  還是熱的呢
Every kind of muffin God ever made, and all of them hot.
很好
Good!
可我們沒有漂亮衣服參加晚宴
But we're not dressed right for such an elegant banquet.
我披著有毛領的紫色絲絨披肩
I'm wearing a long velvet cape with fur on the collar.
你呢
How about you?
我喜歡鉆石
Well, I always liked diamonds myself.
耳環  戒指  裙子上鑲滿鉆石
Rings and bracelets, and a whole dress covered with them.
那些香腸的味好香
Smell those sausages!
我喜歡香腸
I love sausages.
貝琪  貝琪
Becky! Becky!
天哪
Oh, my Lord!
你實在是太神奇了
I think you went a little too far this time.
不是我
It wasn't me.
穿上吧
Go ahead.
我們像是遇見天使了
I feel like I've been touched by an angel.
看
Look!
正是我們點的菜
Just what we ordered.
這讓我有些害伯
I'm a little scared about all of this.
我也是  這東西能吃嗎
Me too. Do you think we shouldn't eat it?
我還沒怕到這地步
I'm not that scared.
謝謝你照顧我  給你們添麻煩了
Thank you for all your kindness. I'm so sorry to inconvenience you.
這沒什么  主人
It is nothing, sahib.
這話
That word...
聽起來很耳熟
It sounds so familiar...
可我不知道它的意思
...yet I don't know what it means.
這不是英語  我們曾經用過
It is not English. We use it where I am from.
在印度
In India.
印度
India...
您懂印度語
You know it?
不
No.
一切都那么模糊
Everything's just a blur.
也許有一天我會想起來
Maybe someday I'll sort it out.
您會的  主人
You will, sahib.
你會的
You will.
你好
Yoo-hoo?
法蘭西斯
Hey! Frances!
等一等
One minute.
我的天
Oh, my God.
法蘭西斯
Frances!
它在哪
Where is it?
項鏈在哪
Where's the locket?
把它給我  把它給我
Give it to me! Give it to me!
這是什么
What is all this?
從哪來的
Where'd it come from?
我不知道  一覺醒來就有了
I don't know. I just woke up and it was here.
是你偷來的  就像你偷了這項鏈
You stole it, didn't you? Just like you stole this locket!
不
No!
你是個骯臟的小賊
You're nothing but a dirty little thief.
我有責任保護這里所有孩子
It's my responsibility to protect the children in this school
不讓她們受你的影響
from animals like you.
但是
But Miss Minchin...
收拾東西  警察會馬上把你帶走
Pick your things. You'll be leaving with the police very shortly!
不  米切思小姐
No, Miss Minchin!
我沒偷東西
I didn't do it.
米切思小姐  我沒偷東西
Miss Minchin, please!
真的沒有
Miss Minchin, I didn't do it!
我說了  你要馬上把她帶走
You heard me. I want her picked up immediately!
你把繃帶取下來了
You've removed the bandages.
不再需要了  我的視力已經恢復
I didn't see there wasn't much point. I can see all right.
進來喝杯白蘭地
That's well, come on in, have a brandy.
別擔心
Don't worry.
他們會相信你的
I'm sure they'll believe you.
不  我得逃出去
No, Becky! I have to get out.
怎么逃  我的房間也被鎖上了
But how? My room's locked too.
警察來了
The police, they're here!
快點  上樓去
Let's go, boys. Step lively now.
快來幫幫我
Quick, help me with this board!
-這邊  -是  女士
-Right this way.  -Yes, madam.
你會掉下去
You'll fall!
我能過去
I can do it.
我會回來接你
I'll come back for you. I promise.
她要干什么
What is she doing?
你給我回來
Get back in here!
-那個小畜牲想溜  -我們會抓住
-The little beast is running away!  -We're trying, miss.
我的天
Good God!
別光站在這里  快去隔壁抓她
Well, don't just stand there! Go next door and find her!
你們最好把她也帶走
And take this one while you're at it.
我昨晚聽見你在夢里喊叫
I heard you calling in your sleep last night.
我有時候做夢  夢見我身體的一部分不見了
Sometimes when I dream, I sense a part of me that's missing.
很奇怪我心里總有樣東西
It's strange, feeling having your heart remember
可腦子想不起是什么
something your mind can't.
見到一個小孩跳過來嗎
She jumped like a little animal.
這個時候會是誰
Who's that at this hour?
讓我們進去
Let us in, man.
學校的一個孩子躲藏進了您家
A child from the school has escaped in your house.
怎么回事
Ram Dass, what's going on here?
打擾了  可有個孩子藏進你家
I'm sorry to interupt you, but there's a child hiding in your house.
-什么  -到樓上去搜
-What?  -Search upstairs.
現在不行
Oh, not now!
拿蠟燭來
Ram Dass, get some candles!
-從閣樓開始搜  -開始
-Start with the attic.  -Let's go.
快點
Quickly!
是誰在那里
Who's there?
檢查柜子  還有床底下
Make sure you check the closets and under the beds!
怎么了
What is it?
為什么哭
Why are you crying?
告訴我  我不會傷害你
Please tell me. I won't hurt you.
告訴我你叫什么名字
Won't you tell me your name?
莎拉
Sara.
多好聽的名字  莎拉
That's such a pretty name. Sara.
爸爸
Papa.
你說什么
What did you say?
爸爸
Papa.
-對不起  -爸爸  是我
-I'm sorry.  -Papa, it's me, Sara.
你不認識我了嗎
Sara, do you know me?
你不記得我了嗎
Oh god papa, don't you remember me?
爸爸是我  你一定記得我  我是莎拉
Papa please, you've got to know me. It's Sara.
想起來了嗎
Remember?
記得印度和瑪亞嗎
Remember India and Maya?
記得拉瑪亞納
Remember the Ramayana...
想想愛米麗  還有那條有媽媽照片的項鏈
...and Emily? And the locket with Mama's picture?
-不  -爸爸  是我
-No.  -Oh, Papa, please!
莎拉
Sara!
爸爸  救我
Papa, please!
你認識這位先生嗎
Do you know this man?
爸爸  告訴他們
Papa, tell them!
這孩子沒有父親  帶她走
This child has no father. Take her away!
爸爸
Papa!
對不起
I'm so sorry.
爸爸
Papa...
莎拉
Sara!
爸爸  永遠不要離開我
Papa, don't ever leave me!
-我想你  -我愛你
-I missed you.  -I love you.
我似乎認不出你了
Well, well, well. I hardly recognized you.
很高興你已經全好了
I'm glad you straightened everything out.
政府歸還了我的全部財產
They released all my property.
我是來跟你道別的
I just came to say goodbye, sir.
感謝你為我所做的一切
...and to thank you for everything you've done for us.
你為我兒子做的更多
No more than you tried to do for my son.
-多保重  -你也一樣
-Take care, Mr. Randolph.  -And you too.
回家是件快樂的事
You must be glad to be going home.
謝謝
Thank you.
我要給你們大家一個驚喜
I have a surprise for you all.
想我了就告訴愛米莉
Whenever you think of me, just tell Emily,
她會把你們的思念帶給我
and she'll get the message to me.
你們摟著她就像在摟著我
And when you hug her, you'll really be getting a hug from me.
我會每天都摟著她
Then we'll hug her every day.
這是她第一次被擁抱
That's the first time anyone's hugged Lavinia.
再見  貝琪
Bye, Becky.
來吧
Come on.
我來了  就來
Yeah, I'm coming, I'm coming.
過來  米切思  我到處找你
Come on! Get over here. I've been looking for you, Minchin.
-把柄拿起來  -我什么時候能休息
-Pick up the bucket.  -Hey, when do I get my break?
跟我來
Follow me!
這桶里是什么  石頭
What do you put in here, rocks?
再見  拉姆·戴斯
Bye, Ram Dass!
-再見  漢納曼  -再會
-Bye, Hanuman!  -Cheerio!